action.
Okay,
I am here with Stu Phillips right now
and uh Stu has agreed to do a a podcast
with me.
Now, I I always have Brad Shfeld on my
podcast as kind of Brad and I um
connected a few years back and he's been
my main go-to guy for discussions with
hypertrophy, but there's always been
another guy out there by the name of Stu
Phillips who
publishes
um Stu, what what uh university are you
at? Mc McMasters University. Yeah, I'm
at McMaster University which is in
Hamilton, Ontario. So that's about uh 30
miles outside of Toronto. But I'm
actually coming to you from uh I'm in
the UK right now. So I'm on a a research
leave. So I'm at Lurburg University just
outside of Ningham. So we're I think
we're 8 hours or 7 hours different. I
don't know. Yeah. So, but Stu does a ton
of research in the fields of sports
nutrition and hypertrophy and kind of
what what do you mostly look at Stu? Um,
really it's the interaction between uh
exercise, mostly resistance exercise and
protein ingestion and the effects that
that has on the fluctuation in muscle
protein turnover. mostly the synthesis
of new muscle proteins and then um
sometimes if we see something promising
we'll take it out in a in a full-blown
uh training study and we'll look at it
on the outcome of hypertrophy.
So this brings me to my next point. Um,
one of the one of the you have a few big
contributions to our industry and one of
the main ones has been
uh at some point you started to doubt
this hormone myth and this was a lot of
research done by I would say Kramer
would be the main one Kramer and a lot
of his colleagues and for probably
at least 10 years correct me if I'm
wrong maybe even longer we all everyone
in the field it just it was accepted as
gospel that if if you want to get
muscular you need to be doing these big
compound lifts. Um, which isn't to say
we shouldn't do these big comp compound
lifts, but our explanation was that
you're going to do a set of squats or a
set of deadlifts or some some big
compound exercise and it's going to
cause you to release a lot of
testosterone and growth hormone and this
is going to travel through your
bloodstream and it's going to make you
more muscular everywhere because this
testosterone coursing through your
blood, it's going to, you know, attach
to the receptor sites of all of your
muscles and you will notice increased
growth on your shoulder. shoulders, your
arms, your entire body because of the
squats.
And again, this isn't to say you
shouldn't be doing your squats and your
deadlifts. It's just to say that our
understanding of the mechanisms were
wrong. And so, Stu, you've done a lot of
research in this area. And you initially
there was a lot of research, sorry, a
lot of resistance coming your way. Like
anything, if you're the mythbuster,
you're the enemy. And so, talk to me
about this line of research.
Yeah. Well, you know, I think you've
you've nicely summarized there what we
would tend to refer to in in my lab as
the hormone hypothesis. And you get this
um rather uh we call it relatively
short-lived because for the most part
it's up and down inside of 15 to 30
minutes uh rise in things like
testosterone, growth hormone, and
insulin like growth factor to name what
I think are the most common ones. And so
most people look at that and those
hormones uh when they're chronically
elevated. So if you have a high level of
testosterone for example from taking you
know exogenous anabolic steroids or you
have low levels of testosterone because
of uh hypogonatism as a condition from
maybe taking drugs if you've been
treated for prostate cancer for example.
It's associated with higher and lower
muscle mass. And so it's intrinsically
appealing to say that those hormones
should have an effect. The main problem
is with that hypothesis is it's never
really been interrogated. It was just a
you know well look these hormones go up
they are present in high concentrations
but it's it's a very very short period
of time and when you look and measure
their concentrations they're really not
elevated that much above what we usually
fluctuate up and down throughout a day.
So, uh, we don't think that they're
tremendously elevated, per se. They're
just really on the sort of high end of
normal for 15 minutes. And, and it's
really hard to ascribe uh, a function to
a hormone like that in such a short
period of time. So we've conducted a
series of studies where we we tried to
sort of push through manipulating models
um and to see whether we could pick up
an effect of that first on stimulating
protein synthesis and then subsequently
on stimulating hypertrophy and you know
we we're up at around I think six or
seven different studies right now where
we've been unable to to see an
association between the rise in in
testosterone or growth hormone or
insulin like growth factor and
stimulation of protein synthesis or
hypertrophy. Uh and so you know we've
sort of looked for this mechanism that's
been thought to be there and we've just
found no evidence of it. So, you know, I
mean, absence of evidence isn't evidence
of absence and and it but but you know,
the correlative argument is the one that
was put forward before and we we haven't
seen any association with now we've had
I think over about a hundred individuals
where we've looked at this relationship
and and we've just been a unable to find
it. So, I'd 100% agree with what you're
saying about these big compound lists.
very useful, great hypertrophy, you
know, uh, great in terms of enhancing
strength and of course you should be
doing them, but the mechanism for how
they work is probably more local within
the muscle than it is to do with the
hormones per se.
So, let me kind of summarize here. Um,
you have done acute studies looking at
increased muscle protein synthesis
immediately following the workout. You
will always see that hormones are indeed
elevated
but and you will see muscle protein
synthesis elevated for the muscle that
was trained but the muscle that was not
trained you will not see increases in
muscle protein synthesis even though
hormones are higher. Exactly. And you've
also done training studies long-term to
see if you know 8 weeks of training or
whatever is going to increase muscle
proteins or increase hypertrophy for the
muscle that's not being trained and you
will not see that. Um, exactly. And so
it mostly comes down to yes, these
compound lifts work or the these the
exercise works because it's it's
building hypertrophy in the muscle that
it's highly activating but not the
muscle that's not being activated. Yeah.
Exactly. So there's there's no crossover
to a a muscle that is you know being
bathed in these hormones where it's
supposed to work. There's no hypertrophy
in sightes that are you know distant
from the ones being exercised. And
similarly when we enhance the exposure
of even an exercise muscle. So we get
somebody to do some arm curls and then
we follow it with a big leg workout or
even vice versa. It it doesn't really
matter. So you would think that the arm
should just you know it should grow much
bigger than the other arm if you're just
exercising it alone. But we don't see
any effect there. And and it's hard to
it's hard to budge people away from sort
of you know that central dogmatic
thinking. And all we're trying to do of
course with this is to say well you know
if there is a mechanism it's pretty
subtle uh it doesn't really have a huge
effect and we think more of that
hypertrophy is due to things that are
happening locally within the muscle. So
we know for example that that things
like uh muscle satellite cells which are
these important cells that contribute uh
nuclei to growing muscle fibers are may
be enhanced by these hormones or
something even produced within the
muscle locally is important but we don't
think that these circulating systemic
you know in the bloodstream uh hormones
are that important. And so my takeaway
with this is has always been don't real
like we got to a I remember back in the
day Stu I don't know if you ever
followed but I I was I can think back to
these articles from this was probably 13
14 years ago I I used to read I was
always an avid researcher and I used to
read these websites like Cyberpunk and
hit or hard gainer and it it would
always tell you to just stick to a few
exercises and kind of the the
high-intensity training philosophy was
just do I think the workouts would be
like a set of squats or trap bar
deadlifts and then if you pick the
squats you would follow it up with a set
of straight leg deadlifts and then maybe
a set of bench a set of bent over rows
and you're done or maybe a set of
weighted dips or weighted chins and
you're done. And you know, sometimes
people would tweak it and add in their
own things, but it would the premise was
you would get muscular all over from
getting stronger at these lifts. And
while I always my I learned from
everything. So with HIT, I learned
progressive overload is the most
important. The first set is the most
important.
But, uh, if you want to if you want your
traps to grow or if you want your delts
to grow or if you want a certain muscle
to grow, you should probably be doing
some isolation movement for it rather
than just thinking that your squats are
deadlifts. Now, that's not to say you
won't get big triceps from bench press
because the triceps are highly
activated, but I always think of
bodybuilding and physique training like
think of the muscle that you want to get
to grow and make sure you're highly
activating it. Is that your consensus as
well? 100%. Yeah. I mean, it's it's not
going to grow if it's not, you know,
you're not activating or hitting the
fibers. You can you can have a little
bit of a hormonal rush, but just
remember that, you know, these hormones
last the the spike comes up, it's high
at 15, it's maybe a little bit higher or
coming down by 30. 60 minutes after the
workout, it's gone. And and that's a
situation that's remarkably different
from an argument that continually gets
put forward, which is, well, steroids
work. And I'm like, yes, of course they
work, but that's elevation of
testosterone to five times normal, 24/7
for however long you take the steroids.
And that's a very different situation
from that very transient and relatively
speaking low uh elevation in in these
hormones that you see after exercise.
But you're 100% on the money. you've got
to activate the muscle to make it grow.
And so that indicates that it has to be
something that's fairly local to the
muscle that's really driving the the
whole stimulus. If hormones have a role,
it's pretty small. We think you bring up
a very good point. You know, I was um
completely naive to a lot of the
bodybuilding and powerlifting worlds and
how much anabolic steroids they were
actually taking. And I started finding
out some of the cycles they were on and
it's like you do the math and they're
they're taking, you know, upwards of
2,000 some people even like 4,000 mil uh
milligrams a week of stuff. And the the
average human male makes like, you know,
7 milligrams a day of testosterone.
Yeah. And so if we're making between, I
don't know, 70 and like 100 milligrams a
week of testosterone and someone's
injecting themselves with two th 2,000
milligs of different substances per
week, then that's 20 times over what you
know what what the average male is
making. Of course, that works. It's
going to make you a lot more muscular
cuz round the clock you're having this
extremely highly elevated um anabolic
maloo going on in in your system. But
you can't compare that to doing a a
highintensity workout where afterwards
your levels are going to be what are are
they doubled? Are they tripled? I don't
really know. But yeah, for the most part
they they go up two to three times what
they are at rest or before the workout.
And they and they stay that way for
usually about half an hour, sometimes a
little longer. And then what you see
afterwards is actually they tend to come
down a bit a little bit lower. And it's
just I mean that's the way hormones
work. And what you have to remember is
our hormones fluctuate like this
throughout a day when you're you know
taking steroids. They're up here and
they stay up here and that's just you
know that's not what we do biologically,
right? So the the kind of like the area
under the curve or whatever wouldn't be
that affected throughout the course of
24 hours because you'd get the 30 minute
spike and then then they dip down and
then they climb back to normal or they
might be elevated. They might stay
slightly elevated but if you look at and
but the another important factor is
anabolic and catabolic hormones will be
elevated. So uh you'll have growth
hormone IGF-1 and testosterone that are
elev elevated. You'll have cortisol and
maybe some other things that are
elevated and so it's net effect on
muscle protein synthesis. Again the
muscle being activated will grow but the
muscles not being activated that the
effect on them is going to be minimal.
So make sure you're working the muscles
that you want to grow.
Now, uh, I always, it's funny cuz you
read other people's research and then,
you know, we all read a lot of different
research and I've always been curious
about some other areas
like the effect of I have come across
research showing that testosterone
increases strength through increased
calcium release out of the sarcolemma or
something like this. So, I always
thought that it would be good to kind of
keep t good for strength
um to keep testosterone elevated if you
can or to try out strategies.
And I have tried over the over the
course of my training career like daily
training with squats and things like
that, which I used to be a fan of, but
it I just think people uh that certain
Olympic weightlifting coaches would
recommend this and some people see
really good results from it. But I also
I've kind of shifted away from that
because I think you can do squats three
times a week and see great results. But
I was always curious about why some
people see such great results with this
such high frequency because in theory
you need to repair, you need to, you
know, you stimulate the muscle and then
you need it, you need to rest and
recuperate and let it grow. But I have
some colleagues that when they started
doing the high frequency squatting,
their strength went through the roof. I
don't think you can keep that up in, you
know, indefinitely. But I do think a lot
of lifters have like a few month window
where they can try out this new
stimulus, this high frequency stimulus
and see good results from it. And I
always wondered if it was due to the
the I don't know. I don't know why it
is. It's due to the skill component or
is it there's something to do with
hormones or something? Because they
would say they don't get they don't the
soreness kind of goes away. They don't
feel as stiff. And I don't know why this
I don't know why this is.
Yeah, we we don't know either. But we've
done enough training studies now and
I've looked at guys who were trained and
guys who were untrained to to sort of
you in in my mind I think there's a
continuum of sort of the ability to
adapt and and and people who are
lifetime lifters have sort of figured
out that they have some propensity to be
strong or to be muscular. They enjoy the
activity and they've clearly probably
got some genetic predisposition towards
either getting stronger, gaining muscle
mass, a combination of the both. And in
doing so, then they probably got an
enhanced repair and regeneration
capacity. So they're they're able to
withstand volumes of exercise that, you
know, most mere mortals would uh would
pale at. So, you know, what they have
that um the rest of us don't um is is
hard to say right now, but what we do
see in all of these training studies,
and I I know it sort of irritates some
people because they think there's
something that, you know, we're not
switching on, is we see a variation in
response that's pretty substantial. So,
we see people that are, you know, big
responders in terms of strength and
hypertrophy. you see people that are
they just it and it's not for lack of
work, they just don't tend to get as
strong. Uh they they find it harder to
train. Um and they don't gain as much
muscle. Uh you you could argue that, you
know, there's various things you can
tweak with that person to get them to
respond. And my answer is probably yes,
but I don't think if you're in the
bottom 20% of nonresponders
that you're ever going to leap from
there to the top 20%. We could maybe
move you into the next 20th percentile.
Um, but I think you're always going to
be sort of down that end. And you know,
uh, that that has to be something
genetic in my mind. And and the question
as to what it is is is pretty hard to
determine to be honest with you. Yeah,
this is a good line of research um by c
certain researchers out there that are
looking at this stuff. I remember a few
years back I wrote an article for
teenage called the truth about
bodybuilding genetics and some of the
some of the p it's something we don't
like to talk about because we're trying
to encourage people to exercise and lift
weights and talking about the benefits
of lifting weights and we're trying to
tell everyone you can radically
transform your physique. And some of
these studies, they looked at a lot of
subjects and there were they they coined
some of them non-respon non-responders
and I can't remember the exact details
but
a a large percentage I don't know if it
was 20% but were did not see much
results at all and they took people
through I think it was an arm routine
like biceps and triceps exercise twice a
week for like 12 weeks. I mean you would
think you would grow from that. You
should see if you're if you're on train
and you start doing twice a week of arm
training, your arms should grow. And I
think the difference between the top
responders, the top responders double
their strength and increase their
hypertrophy by like, you know, 50 to 70%
or something like that. And then the
non-responders gain no strength and no
muscle mass at all. And so then they
they did a follow-up study to this and
took biopsies of the the top responders
and the non-responders and they saw all
sorts of things that were different.
They saw that
uh the satellite cells that you talked
about earlier that satellite cell
mechanism was impaired with the
non-responders in that not only were
they not getting the satellite cells to
to donate their nuclei, but they also
weren't replenishing. Whereas the the
best responders would donate their
satellite cells and then they'd go in
and look at the satellite pool and it
would be higher than it was before. So
they'd have this super compensated
satellite cell pool and then I think a
lot of the IGF-1 and different growth
factors were way lower in the
non-responders. And so some people's
physiology is just built to respond and
to grow and other people just don't have
that. Yeah. and and and it shouldn't be
maybe as big a shock uh to people as you
would think. I mean muscular growth and
hypertrophy is a fairly complex
physiological process and I think we're
learning more and more each day that you
know the underpinnings of a lot of
chronic diseases and a lot of things
have a genetic component to them and so
why would it surprise anybody that
muscular growth has a genetic component
to it. I'm not saying it's it's entirely
governed by genetics, but you know, uh,
if this is the mean and everybody
dubtales out, then there's always going
to be these sort of special individuals
out here. And, you know, these guys have
obviously figured something out early in
life. They lifted a few weights. And,
you know, you've seen these guys, I'm
sure, is that, you know, they they just
seem to grow in front of your eyes. And,
you know, we've done enough training
studies now where we we sort of seen
about seven or eight of those
individuals and and about a hundred. And
so it's, you know, that's the one and a
half, two and a half%, the small tail
there. And these guys put on phenomenal
amounts of muscle. They get way
stronger.
And, you know, it's it's a revelation to
them sometimes because none of them are,
you know, are particularly active before
that, but they just have something that
makes them special. And then you say,
you know, what does your dad look like?
What do your brothers look like? and
they're all bigger guys, you know, and
so, you know, I'm beginning to believe
it more and more. I think we're going to
see in the next few years some research
that'll begin to delineate some of that.
Well, what's interesting, a couple side
notes from this line of discussion is
that one, this is why it's important to
do studies with ample subjects because
there's so much variation.
Why it's why anecdotes aren't always,
you know, you can't always rely on
anecdotes. Like this got me completely
jacked. You should do it. Well, you
might be a good responder. And second of
all, our industry, so many of the people
in our industry like to look at the
biggest guy and go to him for advice and
follow his routine. And a lot of times
that guy's just the luckiest in terms of
genetics. Sure.
Okay, moving on. Um there was a a paper
that your lab uh published um by uh
Mitchell. I can't remember the I didn't
write down the title of the paper but uh
y something about heavier weights. Um so
another area of research that your lab
has um and and by the way Stu I I've I
speak for I'm a fellow guy who likes to
kind of bust myths and misconceptions
and it's I want to say I I have a lot of
respect for you because it's draining.
It is so draining to the point, Steu,
where sometimes you I have some things
that I've kind of discovered in in my
lab. Uh, I have EMG and Forest Plate
and, you know, I don't I don't have like
a full-on like a lab like a university
would, but I have a couple things that
I've found and I I'm just something I
found a year ago and I'm like, I'm going
to wait for the I wait for it to be
published because I I don't want to be
accused of I don't want I don't have the
energy right now to battle all the
powerlifters who are going to tell me
that I'm an idiot and all this stuff.
And sometimes you you know that this is
going to weigh me down. and I'm going to
be accused. I'm going to be, you know,
mocked. And uh you got you have to fight
through it and you have to read on the
social media this, you know, the people
who don't understand the research are
going to accuse you of being an idiot
and you're going to have to re, you
know, have to explain these things to
the these these types adnauseium because
they just don't understand, you know,
they they're they're hellbent. They
don't want to change their opinion on
something. And so when you have guys
like you who are out there busting myths
and misconceptions in the name of
science, I commend you guys because it's
it's so much easier to just not do any
research and be that guy who's oh this
guy this guy's telling us not to do
squats and deadlifts. Apparently he
doesn't think, you know, and it's like,
no, that's not what we're saying. That's
not the point. This guy's saying not to
lift heavy weights. No, you're not
saying that. you're just saying you can
get the same growth through lighter
weights. And so that's another area of
research that your lab has come out with
over the last several years and we're
heading more and more in this direction.
Um you lab your lab has lots of studies
now probably correct me if I'm wrong
maybe like six or seven where showing
that lighter loads
taken close to failure can induce just
as much hypertrophy as heavier weights.
Um, and kind of as long as effort is
there, that if the effort is there and
you're working hard, then you can kind
of choose the load that makes you that
that if you're a type of lifter that
does not like heavy loads, you don't
have to do heavy loads. If if you're
just a physique person, if you're just
training for hypertrophy, you can train
in the 10 just with 10 rep maxes or even
20 rep maxes, possibly even 30 rep maxes
and see similar growth as you could as
if you were doing heavy weights. Uh talk
about this and then don't let me forget
because I want to talk about the
Mitchell paper with the type one and two
fiber growth, but talk about this topic
for for a minute. Right. So, first of
all, thanks for the the comments about
being a mythb, but I don't think we set
out to to bust myths, but um we
certainly like to challenge dogma and um
you know, this was one of the things
that we looked at. We looked at certain
statements from certain organizations
saying is that and it wasn't that you
know, you can only get hypertrophy from
lifting heavy, but it said that lifting
heavier was superior to lifting lighter.
and they name a few sort of percentage
of repetitions that I just said, you
know, there's really not enough evidence
to say that. I don't think that that's
the case. And so we sort of went back to
basic physiology and said if you take a
muscle to fatigue, it really doesn't the
muscle doesn't understand how it really
got to fatigue. Fatigue is fatigue. uh
and according to something called the
size principle then fatigue means is
your muscle is trying to sustain a given
level of force and it will do that by
recruiting certain motor units. So type
traditionally type two or the fast
twitch or type one motor units. And so
if you get there through lifting heavy
loads, we know that you sort of get to a
certain rep and then bang, you can't
generate the force. If you get there
through a lighter load, it's sort of
different. At the end of the rep, you're
kind of doing this sort of thing and
your muscles kind of shaking, but it's
still fatigue. And if the size
principle, which is, you know, sort of
very central uh tenant of muscle
metabolism and and muscle physiology is
correct, then you should have activated
or been close to anyway full activation
of muscle fibers. And if that's the
case, then our thought was that the load
and how you got there mattered less than
actually getting there. So, lighter
loads, heavier loads. Um, and we
certainly didn't get into this wanting
to rewrite the strength and conditioning
manuals. You know, I' I've said to a lot
of people if you want to get stronger,
you have to lift heavy weights. So, you
know, there's no ifs, ands, or buts
about that. That's that's very clear.
This is not about strength. If you want
if your strength is your goal, you've
got to be going heavier. But if you're
just how I would say the majority of
people when they start training with
you, they don't care about strength.
They want a good physique. They don't
come to you and say, "I just want to be
strong and I have powerlifting goals in
mind." They say, "Just help me get a
better physique." Sure. So, so it's
about hypertrophy. It's about muscular
growth and changing muscle size and
then, as you say, improving your
physique. So, you know, we did some
experiments where at first we measured
protein synthesis, which a lot of people
quite correctly point out. They go,
"Well, that's not hypertrophy." And I'm
like, "You're 100% correct, but we need
the proof of the principle first." And
so we noticed that the protein synthetic
response was as good with the low loads
to fatigue as it was with the high lows
to fatigue. And so we said well look you
know this is at least you know a pretty
good grounding to move on to a training
study. So in the Mitchell study what we
did was you know we randomize people and
again you know it's a contrived design.
We try and do studies where we minimize
variability. So, you know, my one leg
versus my other leg is always less
variability within me than between me
and between you, for example. A lot of
people don't like the design. I I get
it. But, um, so the main point was this
load, you know, this leg trains with
heavy load, this leg trains with light
load, and the hypertrophy is the same at
the end of, you know, 10, 12, whatever,
however, many weeks. This leg gets
stronger than this leg, which is exactly
what you'd expect. Um but you know the
proof of the principle that heavier
loads are superior to lighter loads is
just not there. So and I think in
fairness to the particularly the
bodybuilders and the physique people
they understand this that they do they
they don't tend to lift they can't lift
heavy all the time because of the volume
that they do. So they cycle on and off
and what they notice is that their
strength might go down but I think if
they take things to fatigue there's
really not a lot of change in their
muscle mass or their physique that stays
pretty much intact and so you know uh
even at its you know sort of scientific
best uh I think in the gym people have
figured this stuff out but it it it so
what it meant to us is that the
recommendations for generation of
muscular hypertrophy weren't Exactly
correct. And I know since you've
probably had Brad on your show a number
of times is that you know he and I have
discussed this over email and you know
he's he's argued that well you know we
know from studies etc etc but um uh I
don't know whether he's shared it with
you but he's got some research that
actually I think tends to fit with what
we're showing as well. And so um well I
will because I'm he's maybe coming over
to our site. Yeah. Yeah. And and that's
a that's an God, I have all these
tangents I want to talk about. So, I'm
going to I'm going to touch on this in a
second, but a couple things that I was
trying to mentally keep in mind while I
was listening to you. First of all, you
still see these charts with these
telling you what and it's like one to 10
reps will do or one to five reps will do
this for you. Five to 10 will do this.
And it's not that that's not that way.
No. Now, back to the size principle. I
first started hearing about the size
principle from Carpinelli, who obviously
got it from other people, but he's kind
of the person who first started saying
this. Yeah. Take a take a set to failure
and you're going to activate the muscles
to the same degree whether you're using
a heavy weight or a lightweight. Yeah.
And this activation, a lot of people
nowadays kind of think activation isn't
all that. And I'm like, so what? You can
just how the how's the muscle going to
grow then if it's not activating right?
If you want a muscle to grow, you got to
and now we could argue what you know
what what are the optimal protocols, but
you you got to be choosing an exercise
that that does highly activate that
region. Now, I was very doubtful this
and I wanted to tell you this because
you you changed my mind and this is what
research researchers should do because I
had done a ton of EMG research. Yeah.
Yeah, but I had never I would every
every one of my protocols I like doing
case studies. I like taking someone and
having them hooked up to the electrodes
for three straight hours where we do a
ton of stuff. I can't have them go into
failure on all their sets or they'd
fizzle out. So, we'll take a, you know,
a five rep max load and I'll have them
do two or three reps. It's very it's
it's that's important because they're
not getting fatigue. So, I can test them
and it depends on the exercise. If it's
something that's a more of a high rep
movement, I might have them do eight
reps, but they could do 20 to 30. But I
do this because I'm sparing fatigue so
they can do so I can test them on 20 to
30 different exercises, right? But I
never had them go to failure. And so
when I started seeing your research, so
I always was the opinion that heavy
weights are better because when you when
you take heavier weights, you start off
high right off the bat. You get Yeah.
Sure. And then I started taking lighter
loads and going to failure. Now I will
say it it does depend on the exercise.
You don't always and and there is a
sweet spot in my my opinion where you
can't you can't just take you know I
can't just do body weight arm curls. You
know there's 100% right? There's some
point where and Brad and I I don't know
if Brad told you this. We're trying to
publish a a a paper right now with leg
leg press. Right. We looked at 30%
versus 75, I believe, and the 30% did
not reach the 75. But that doesn't mean
what it means is that there's going to
be some sweet spot somewhere. And it
might depend on the exercise. It might
depend on the muscle group. But I will
tell you with glutes, I had done body
weight stuff. When you do body weight
squats or body weight glute bridges, the
muscle activation doesn't keep going up.
it kind of it's like it's aerobic or
something because you're it stays put.
So I was always doubtful this stuff and
I was like no way heavier weights are
better. But then I started doing, you
know, a set of 20 to to failure, a real
set of 20 to absolute failure, set of
20, whatever. I'd get 22 reps. And lo
and behold, say I did squats or hip
thrusts or deadlifts, it doesn't matter.
It whatever I would get with like say a
five rep max load, I would end up
getting with a 20 whatever failure ended
up being, say 22 reps. Yeah. that peak
those peaks would end up matching the
peaks that I got with the five rep set.
And what I found was when I I would
start off with something, say I say I
was getting, you know,
peaks of 80 right off the bat with like
a hip thrust, I would end up on my 20
second rep getting a peak of 160. It
would double throughout the set and I
would end up getting the same as what I
did with the heavier loads. And so I
realized that's really cool because the
practical applications of this is that
you know the the elderly or in rehab
situations, you don't want to be loading
them up heavy right away or you don't
want necessarily want to go there. Have
them do have them do the lighter weights
for higher reps while keeping form
really good. There's going to be a lower
chance of injuring themselves, right? So
they could the hypertrophy they can get.
Now back to the Mitchell paper. Oh, so
anyway, this is what researchers should
do. I I'm skeptical what you're saying,
but I'm gonna go experiment on my own.
Oh, he's right. You know, yeah, we
should use more of that instead of, oh,
you're an idiot, but then I'll never
test out what you're saying. Um, which
is what I see often in the field. The
critical people will never change their
mind. They'll never go do the research
on their own. They'll never go do any
experiments. They'll just continue to
criticize it and go, "Oh, what does the
researcher know?" And by the way, Stu,
you lift weights yourselves. You're a
strong guy. Yeah. I'm I'm sort of but
I'm I'm the complete middle of the road
guy. I'm not the big guy. I don't think
I'm the little guy, but I'm I'm I'm
about as average as they Everybody hates
to be average, but yeah, I I mean, I'm
not I'm not super strong and I'm not
super big, but but I'm not small. I'm
not weak either. So, but they they the
the researchers are always painted out
to be these lab coats that don't, you
know, do you even lift? And it's not
that's in my experience cuz I've met a
lot of the sport science researchers
around the world at this point and most
of them were old coaches and lifters
themselves and that's what drew them
into the field. It's not like they're
this these esoteric
you know nerds that have never lifted a
weight. I didn't I didn't get into this
because you know I mean I enjoy being in
a lab and I enjoy science but yeah you
know I played rugby I played ice hockey.
I played you know football. Um, and most
of the lifting I did was for, you know,
sports to get bigger and stronger faster
and everything. I, you know, I have to
admit to never having, you know, lifted
to improve my physique, per se, but, you
know, yeah, I've I've got some genetic
predisposition, you know, I tend to look
like that rather than to be like this.
And so, yeah, but but I'm I'm not that
big. But the point is we're we're not
these esoteric nerds that don't lift. We
we work out and are there is value like
this the recommendations get twisted
sometimes. You're not saying like in the
high in the hormonal stuff you're not
saying don't do squats and deadlifts.
You're saying it gets twisted into that.
You're saying do exercises for that body
part for which you want to grow. With
the high rep stuff you're not saying
don't ever do low reps. You're saying
that you can get good growth out of
doing lower weight for higher reps.
100%. And I and I think a lot of this is
driven by and you mentioned a couple of
situations for older people and
rehabilitation, but also, you know, from
my own personal perspective, the the
older I get, all that I find now is, you
know, I squat, I deadlift, I I mean, I
do all the compound stuff, but it's
harder to recover. And, you know, so to
me now, it it's a lifetime game. And and
I'm looking at, you know, doing this
until I'm into my, you know, 70s, 80s,
or whenever. Um, and so, you know, part
of it was driven by how can you still
maintain this and yet allow more
recovery because if I think if there's
anything that happens with aging, it's
the ability to recover is is, you know,
bit a bit messed up for whatever reason.
Uh, so, you know, part of it was driven
by that. And, uh, again, personal
experimentation, you just sort of say,
well, I'm going to drop things down.
Gez, you know, I wasn't I don't want to
do that because, you know, he lifting
heavy is the way to go. Uh, and you find
actually, yeah, okay, my strength went
down, but muscle mass wise, nothing
changed. And I said, you know, there's
something to this. So, you know, yeah,
you figure a lot of this stuff out
yourself and then you do some reading
and then when that statement gets made
that lifting heavy is superior, you
know, you begin to think about the
physiology and you're like, you know,
that's that doesn't make sense actually
if you think about it. But but I agree
with you is that 30% for a a leg press
is not going to do it because you could
probably do 70 or 80 repetitions for
some people. So maybe you've got to
choose something like 50, right? Versus,
you know, 80 eventually at 50 after your
33rd rep, you know, your legs are
shaking like a sewing machine. It hurts.
I I'll agree. Yep. But it's still
fatigue. And that brings me to good
fiber activation. I don't want to forget
this because this is an important point
because Brad is doing research right now
with with
30 whatever 30 reps or a certain
percentage I can't remember but the PE
it is very I mean I've read studies back
in the day where these people had to
drop out because they get so much
nausea. You know it's it's it's not like
who whoever thinks that 20 reps is for
wimps. We're not talking about just
holding on to pink dumbbells going like
this. We're talking about taking
something to failure. I would rather do
a set of five than a set of 20 to
failure. I like I remember back in the
day being able to do squat 225 lbs for
like 25 reps. And I could deadlift 315
for 25 reps. And it was the worst thing
you you want mentally. Oh my god, it is
not easy. So yeah, I I what I like to do
is stick to my in my own training. It's
funny you mentioned cuz I think I was
listening to uh
um what's his face? Steve Job Steve Jobs
audio book and he was talking about a
lot of his innovation drove from things
that he wanted for himself. They would
create the products that they wanted.
You know the iPod they wanted one
themselves. And it's funny because in
our field we we're going to be driven
towards research. You know I want to
benefit my own training. So I want to
see if my you know you you form a
hypothesis. I wonder if yeah my strength
will drop out but I wonder if I can keep
my hypertrophy from just sticking to
just lighter weight. And then you do you
test the hypothesis you see and then you
okay let's test this with a larger group
of people right? And um and and and so a
lot of our own research gets driven from
things that interest us. That's natural.
But for the people who think that train
lighter loads is wimpy, man, they
they're clearly not going to failure
with lighter loads because it is not
wimpy. There's nothing wimpy about it.
Is hard to do. Um it hurts. It hurts.
And uh if you haven't done it and and
you know try it yourself and uh it
you're in for a rude awakening, I tell
you, right? You're in for a rude
awakening uh once you actually start
going to failure with lighter loads. So
this is just to say that this isn't to
say don't do heavy weights. It's just to
say lighter loads taken close to
muscular failure is a very potent hyper
hypertrophic stimulus. Now back to the
Mitchell paper. Yeah. So the size
principle states that if you take
say you do a one rep max to failure
you're going to recruit all the
available motor units because you are
doing a maximal effort. But if you take
a lighter load, like we said, you start
out and it keeps increasing each rep
until when you go to absolute failure to
counteract fatigue, the muscles get
activated higher to try to match the
force production. And you will end up
getting as high as that maximal effort
at at the point of failure. But it goes
backwards. With that heavy load, you're
supposed to recruit all the units,
including all the type one units. And
this might not be the case or maybe they
need more time under tension which they
get with the heavier the lighter loads
because what we're seeing with the
Mitchell paper is that you will get
taking doing heavy weight doing lighter
weight you get similar amounts of muscle
hypertrophy
but the heavier weight and the lighter
weight they're similar in terms of type
two muscle fiber growth but the lighter
weight's better in terms of type one
muscle growth. Yeah, and that's a point
that that that Brad and I have discussed
and you know Brad um is fond of the
theory and and it makes a lot of sense
and as you know when you said it right
there is that when you cycle through
those type one um units and yet you know
towards the the fatigue that you get um
then you do engage those fibers probably
more than when you're engaging them you
know down at the lower uh repetitions
and Maybe that's a protective mechanism
to just, you know, hold some of those
fibers and motor units in reserve. Uh,
you know, the third set and then the
fourth set, I'm sure they're coming into
play. Um, but you're right, it it it
seems to be is that the type ones tend
to grow a little bit more. Uh, the
Mitchell paper, we just didn't have the
statistical power to to show anything
significant. Um, so the goal is, you
know, we have a study underway to try
and see whether that's the case. And so
the biopsy data from enough men will
will show us whether that's the case.
And so and I know in in concert with
some of the work that Brad's doing, um
hopefully we can crack this nut and sort
of say, you know, this is why it's
happening. Here's where it's happening
and the reason behind it. But again, so
if you want to um maximize hypertrophy,
then what you're talking about is really
trying to do both forms of training. So
maybe some high intensity and some low
intensity to engage all of the fibers uh
and to mix things up programwise to to
hit the type ones and the type twos. So
that's what I would like to see over
time is
and this is with so much areas of
research. Brad and I talk about this all
the time. We would like to see okay you
people will say this exercise versus
this this exercise but what about if you
do them both? People will say this rep
range versus th this rep range. What if
you do them both? Yeah. And so
personally I think you'd get you'd maxim
if you're looking at a way to maximize
hypertrophy. You know a lot a lot of the
bodybuilders would pyramid. They do
their a variety of they've never stick
to one load. They would do a variety.
And so for optimal maybe it's that you
need to do a certain amount of get a
certain amount of volume in at the at
the lower end and a certain amount at
the higher end. and then you're covering
all your bases. Whether that's the case
remains to be seen, right? Um, some of
the critics of your research will look
at what you mentioned, this crossover
design where you take one leg and do
high reps with it, the other leg and do
low reps with it. And and I I think the
two main criticisms are that you don't
have that that that design you can have
the crossover effect. So some
researchers shows that if you do one leg
just one leg the other leg will get
stronger and will get more muscular due
to the crossover effect because you got
in your brain
uh the the is it the c the the cortex or
whatever it crosses over and you end up
getting but your research shows that
that's pretty that's not so substantial
where it's going to completely skew the
results. Maybe that's responsible for a
couple percent but right a and I think
you know uh Simon Gandavia who's in
Australia has written sort of the
authoritative review on this and he's
even got it down to the sort of
percentage crossover that you would see
in terms of the strength enhancement.
Now the mechanism would be is that the
stronger leg would always pull up the
weaker leg a little bit but it can
account for all the variation and and
what you have to remember and I sort of
explain this to my students when I teach
the undergraduate classes is to say is
that you know research is like building
a house and so we have to build a
foundation first and then we put some
things into place and then we begin to
and you try and build a whole story.
Sometimes you can build a house with
with one paper, you know, it generally
ends up in nature or science or, you
know, New England Journal of Medicine,
right? Uh but in in in physiology that's
not going to happen. And so we have to
build some things along the way. So you
know, first we did the protein synthesis
and then we did a you know unilateral
proof of principle trial. So the next
step is to obviously is to you know to
do the between subjects you know one
group trains like this one group trains
like this but appreciating that as you
go up in the ladder with those
experimental designs the variability
goes gets higher and so the sample size
needs to be bigger and so the money
needs that needs to support it and and
all of these things I know it's not
wasted on most people but you know some
people are it's very easy to criticize
research there's no question about it um
The hardest part I think and my my
skin's grown fairly thick over the years
is when somebody just says, "Oh, well,
you should have done this." And I'm
like, you know, we know we should have
done that, right? But, you know, to jump
from this to this and and miss then
doesn't serve anybody because if you get
this the wrong answer up up at the high
level, then everything's messed up
because then that translates back down.
Everybody says C. So you have to get the
design right and with people because of
this response variation that we see you
just need a lot of people. Um and as I
said the difference in variability
between my two legs and within me is a
lot less than between me and you. So we
start out that way and we build the
story. And so I like that. I've come to
like that design because
the people who argue about the crossover
effect, well, it works both ways. So the
whatever crosses over in this leg to
this leg is going to be so they should
balance each other out. And like you
said, I would love to it's great to use
yourself as the control because you
minimize that interindividual response
effect we talked about earlier. We have
this huge variation. So, and then the
other criticism I'll hear is that you're
not using advanced subjects, but
we'd all like to use advanced
bodybuilders in our research, but a
that's hard to come by, and b it's hard
to get a bodybuilder who's going to be
okay with just training one leg or, you
know, like or sticking to some protocol.
They have their set ways. And C, I'd
argue that
you also you need to start off like what
you're saying, you need to build a
foundation. You need to start off with
the general public. You don't jump right
to the advanced bodybuilders, but I
think you guys have included some
advanced subjects in your train in your
routines and they're seeing the same
results. Correct. Yeah. And again, we're
moving in that direction. And as I said,
you know, if this is the population now,
we're getting down and we're getting
into the smaller and smaller sort of
percentage of people. And if we're
talking about the really big guys now,
as you point out, if I come in, I'm
going to say, okay, you're going to
train this leg this way and this leg
this way, they just look at me like, you
know, man, you're crazy. I'm not, you
know, why would I stop doing what I'm
doing? You know, this this means too
much to me. So, you know, they're hard
to convince. Uh we have had some guys
that are more trained than other and
we're moving into an area now where I
think where I don't know if we're down
in the tail, but we're definitely beyond
uh the mean response. And so most of the
people that we've recruited into this
study that we have going on right now
are more trained. And I think people
need to look around themselves a little
bit and realize is that the people that
as you point out are the bigger guys in
the gym that they always want to get the
advice from because they're big. You
have to ask yourself is it because of
what they do or in spite of what they
do? Because it, you know, some of these
guys like it doesn't appear. They do a
minimal amount of work by comparison to,
you know, where I am right now. I had to
work my ass off to do it. And they just
get it like that. And so it's come a lot
easier to them than it probably has to
most people, I would guess. And my my
experience is that you you just have to
work with a lot of people like you have
done research on so many people by now
that you've seen all the var the
variations in response. But if you're
just a guy who lifts yourself and then
something works for you, you're going to
just, oh, this is the end all be all.
You need to do this program cuz I got
huge from it or I got strong from it.
But you don't you don't know that this
person, you know, you've never trained
enough people to know that not every
exercise works really well for every
body type. Not every method works well
for every person. And so the more people
you train, the more you learn how to
adapt programs to meet to suit the
individual's goals, body type, and
logistics. Um, but uh moving on uh
because I know you got to get going. I
have a couple more questions I want to
ask. I want to get into two two more
areas, protein intake and supplements
because I share a similar outlook on you
on this matter. But real quick, um I
want to talk to because you're one of
the few labs who have actually looked at
cycloplasmic versus myofibrillar
hypertrophy. And I wanted to discuss
this kind of misconception out there
because a lot of times people think that
if you do light weights for high reps,
you're just building fluid. you're just
growing through fluid increase and it's
not functional. And if you do heavy
weights, you know, sets of five, you're
just bu you're building density. You're
building the myofi, you know, you're
building the sarcomirs. And so there's
been this whole um kind of there's so
many articles I've seen over the last 5
years talking about how heavy weights is
functional because you're building the
the the sarcomirs and the the the
myofhibrillar hypertrophy and then
lightweights is not functional and
you're just building cycloplasmic
hypertrophy just the fluid and the like
organels within the the the fiber and
this is not a proper outlook. You do
have there's a little bit of truth to
that maybe, but it's what just by a
minor percentage like if you do sets of
20 versus sets of five, how much of a
difference is a shift are you going to
get in the types of hypertrophy?
So, you know, 60 plus% of what's inside
a muscle fiber are myopibbrals and
they're packed very densely and it's
hard to fit a lot of other things in. So
you know plus or minus I'd say about 5%
that's the sort of variability you have.
But this concept that you get
cycloplasmic versus myofibriller or non
myofibrillar hypertrophy is is
absolutely incorrect. Is there's no way
to hypertrophy and expand organels and
fluid within a muscle fiber that would
fill up enough space to make it grow as
big as the fiber that grew in the heavy
uh group. I I think the misconception is
is that you you can talk about you
people maybe you know put a tape measure
around one bicep one time and said oh
well it grew as much as the other one
but I'm not as strong so it must be you
know hypertrophy of something that's not
force generating.
That's not true. The reason you don't
get as strong is because the
neuromuscular connection between this
and the and the low weight or you know
high repetition arm just isn't as good.
Um, so you know, we know that strength
is is for a large part neuromuscularly
driven. So, you know, this begins to
talk to this and it talks to it more
efficiently. You don't get as much
activation of the co-activated muscle um
at the excuse me, the uh antagonistic
muscle uh and so you get stronger.
Whereas in this arm, you haven't been
doing these strong maneuvers. You still
get the hypertrophy. And so somebody has
come up with this well it's cycloplasmic
versus myofhribriller and and that's you
know and not to disparage people's lines
of research but there's just no evidence
for that. So you know in our hands and
in a lot of other labs if you look at
the percentage of a fiber that is
myofibrillar protein it's 60%
plus or minus I'd say about 5%. So yeah,
in in in endurance athletes, there's a
lot more mitochondria in there, but this
is not what we're talking about when
we're talking about, you know, something
that's done 30 reps. That's not
endurance exercise. It's an
endurance-like exercise versus, you
know, four to five reps. But there's
just um yeah, it's time to sort of put
that's that's a a hard one to put to bed
other than to just say, well, we just
measure the protein content and here's
what it is. Um, it's very simple to do,
but if that's what it takes to to to put
that one to bed, it just sort of seems
to me it's another one of these things.
As a biochemist, I look at the fibers
and I'm like, how could anybody think
that that's right? But there you go.
Yep. Yep. Okay. All right. Two quick
questions and I will let you get going.
The first uh pertains to protein intake.
This is uh debated a lot and it's it's a
it's something that you know I think is
skewed by the bodybuilders who are
taking lots of stero uh steroids
anabolic steroids but cuz you'll see
bodybuilders who are taking in 400 g of
protein a day. Sure. But for guys that
are natural, for guys like you and me
and our most of our listeners and men
and women is what is the optimal amount
and well first let's talk about that.
Yeah. Uh it's really hard to peg it. Um
we have a paper that's going to come out
hopefully really soon. The reviewers
have had a good go at us and so um uh
it's about uh 0.25 25 g of protein per
kilo will maximally stimulate muscle
protein synthesis after a workout. Um,
and so we're thinking that that's the
sort of per meal dose that you might
like to hit. And you can probably do it
about four or five times a day. If you
if you do the math and you sort of
figure everything out, uh, the
calculation that I put out um, and just
as a sort of a ballpark is somewhere
around 1.8 8 gram of protein per
kilogram per day tends to hit this sweet
spot where you know you're going to
maximize muscle growth we think and
beyond that and I'm not saying don't eat
more protein because you got to put
something into the machine but we just
don't think that it's contributing to
muscular growth now you want to eat
twice that much and you feel that's what
you got to do like I said I'm not going
to argue because you know the evidence
is not great um but based on what we
that we know, we understand about how
muscle responds. There's only so many
times you can feed it if you like muscle
in a day and it'll take those amino
acids on board, put them in a protein
and hang on to them. After that, it
actually begins to turn off if you like
and become nonresponsive. And that's a
classic, you know, biological feedback
loop system. And not to say that the
bodybuilders who, you know, take four
grams, you know, they're bigger, but
it's not because of the protein that
they do it. You know, the if they're
lifting heavy and they're in the gym a
lot and if they are on steroids, then
that's driving the bus. And you they
could probably get away with a lot less
protein and still be as big as they are.
But you got to make a choice about what
you're going to eat. And I don't
necessarily think that eating more
protein is a bad thing. So that's sort
of where we stand on that. So this if
you were cuz you're talking in kilograms
because in Canada and Canada and the UK
you guys are logical and use the metric
system but
well actually UK doesn't. So uh but yeah
we're still they talk stones over here.
I don't even know what that is but so in
in the US we go by pounds. So, it comes
to not quite one gram per I always just
tell people cuz it makes it so easy. A
gram per pound of body weight. I've said
that for 10 years as a trainer and it's
a basic rule of thumb.
Could you go could you get the same
doing less? Probably I think again I I I
still come back to this sort of
continuum and I think you know if you're
you're the responder I think you can
certainly do it with less. If you're
this sort of hard gainer, then I think
you can push a little bit more into the
system and a little bit more total
energy into the system and move yourself
up the ladder. You're never going to be
that guy at the other end, but I I think
you can do it. Um, a gram a pound is I
don't have an issue with that. And you
that's 2.2 g per kilo. And you know,
that's that's in the ballpark of you
know, some of the papers we've written.
And you're looking you're saying 1.8 is
sufficient upper end, you know, and
again, what about the lower end? It's a
soft number, right? So, I'd say, you
know, most of the recommendations we've
said, you know, anywhere from, say, 1.6
to 2.2 g per kilo. So, that's a little
bit less than 1 g to about 1 g per
pound. And beyond that, you can eat it,
your body can, you know, digest it and
everything. I just don't think your body
can physically put it into muscle at a
rate fast enough for it not to be used
for other things. And at some point you
tear the nitrogen off of protein and
then you got to pee it out. And that's
what you know humans, mammals and birds
and lizards everybody does that because
nitrogen is it's toxic fundamentally. So
you know so long as we appreciate that
from a biological standpoint and that's
sort of where I kind of end and say well
you know you do what you got to do but
here's my recommendation to you. So as a
a guy who read, you know, I spend more
of my time reading biomechanics
research. We all have our areas that we
like more and then you tend to find
people you trust in the field because I
never full am fully confident with my
opinion unless I've read all the papers.
So I can tell I know what Alan Aragon
thinks on this topic. I know what you
think. I know what Brad thinks. I like
to listen I have a friend Menow
Hanselman who's smart on this. He likes
he goes by the lower end and he he's
read all the papers and he can critique
the papers and he'll say there's no
evidence showing that above and he likes
the lower end. I know Eric Helms did a
review paper. Yeah, I believe he has
some an actual experimental paper coming
out, but again, it's the there's a lot
of ways to do it, but from Alan Aragon
and Brad's stuff, I'm kind of leaning
towards you don't have to eat eight
times a day like we used to think. But I
do think there's a sweet spot where it's
you're not going to get maximum
anabolism from eating one time a day.
You need a certain amount of lucine
signaling. So, probably three times a
day, I would think, would be the
minimum. And then you we say three to
five. Three to five. But that's what
most people do anyway. Sure. If you like
if you like eating twice a day, you
probably aren't going to get your
maximum response is, you know, cuz
you're going to have to eat, you know,
if you're a 200 lb guy, you're going to
have to eat a lot of protein in one
sitting. you might and you're not going
to get as as much of the lucine trigger.
So, is it better to eat more frequently?
Maybe. But the point of Brad and Allen
stuff is it's not as important as people
think it is. Like, it wasn't as it
wasn't like, you know, back in the day,
we talk about myths and misconceptions.
I remember from the the Body for Life
book, um I thought I had to be eating
eight times a day or I was going to go
catabolic. And I remember go right
before I'd go to sleep, I'd be full, but
I'd slug down a protein shake. I
remember at one point in my life in my
mid20s I was even I'd wake up in the
middle of night to go use the restroom
and I'd slam a protein shake and that's
probably going overboard you know so
yeah for sure so around 1.8 8 g per
kilogram of body weight, that comes to
less, that comes to probably what, like8
g per pound of body weight. And so if
you weigh 200 lb and you have 160 g per
day, you're probably hitting your bases.
If you get a little bit more, the
benefits to having a little bit more
protein are that well, the thermic
effect of protein is higher. The satiety
effect is a little bit higher. So, you
might have a good a better physique
because you burn off more and you're not
as hungry. The drawbacks are that you
might waste that protein. Uh, and that
those those you could be having carbs
and fat, which could fuel your workouts
better. The higher fat could benefit
hormone production. The higher carbs
could benefit fuel your workouts better.
Yeah, but the higher carbs could also
contribute to in decreasing insulin
sensitivity and the higher fat could go
towards blah blah blah. It all comes
down to figuring out your optimal
system. Everything's a give give or
take. You've got to experiment with
calories and macronutrients, but you
don't need to feel compelled to be
eating so much darn protein that
everyone's saying, you know, they we
used to say probably 1.8 g per kilo is
sufficient.
That's what I would think. Yeah. Yep.
Okay. Good. We're on the same page
there. And then last topic and then I
will let you get going is supplements.
You have done a ton of research on
supplements. I get asked this question
all the time. It's not that I'm
anti-supplements.
It's just that I think that people spend
so much
focus on supplements when they're not.
Usually you look at their diets and
they're not eating the to me the the
drawbacks of spending your money on all
these supplements is that you could be
getting more high quality foods. You
could be going to the store and buying,
you know, cuz me like I I sit there,
God, I wish I was a celebrity, a
millionaire. I'd be I'd have a chef and
I'd be eating this every day. I love ai
tuna. I love filetmenon. I love, you
know, the nicer. And it's like, well, if
you aren't buying your supplements so
much supplements, you could be eating
that. and enjoying your meals more. What
supplements have and and I know we can
find we can cherrypick studies and find
evidence for every supplement working,
but what supplements out there have a
ton of evidence showing that they are
very effective for muscle hypertrophy
and decreasing body fat? Yeah. So, I
mean there's there's really when you
build the hierarchy and you look at the
evidence and you know, we reviewed a lot
of this stuff. Uh, obviously protein.
Um,
but protein only if you're not you can
get the protein in your foods. Oh, sure.
Cuz I like taking whey. I like my whey
protein. Do you take like whey
supplementation? Yeah, I do. I do whey
with my breakfast meal and I'm usually I
I work out first thing in the morning.
I'm usually fasted and then I and then I
have my breakfast. So that's you know my
breakfast is is big. Um, so at that
time, you know, I think it's worth it
and I get a big satiety response and,
you know, I feel really full and it's a,
you know, for me that's how I start my
day. Uh, you could talk you I mean,
you're talking about creatin. Um, I'd
sort of give that an an A grade. Um, and
then after that things tend to drop off
fairly rapidly. There's a little bit of
excitement about HMBB. Uh, I'm not
overly convinced with that as a
supplement. Uh well the HMBB uh is
this is coming out of Wilson Dr. Dr.
Jacob Wilson's lab and there's only one
study so far, right? With the HMBB uh
what is it? F uh the certain the free
acid the free acid which this is
interest I always when there's a new
study I chalk it up as interesting but
we need to learn more right and so you
know the way I view supplements is if
you're building the pyramid um and the
peak is you know whatever it is physique
or performance or whatever the
supplement is kind of the cherry on the
top and so the base is still get to
training good diet good sleep etc And
you know, obviously, well, the
foundation would be genetics, I suppose.
Um, and then right at the very top is,
you know, there's a little bit of icing
in a cherry, and that's where the
supplements sit. I I don't think that
they're the difference between, you
know, this guy down here and this guy up
here. Um, I believe they would take sort
of everybody and probably shift them a
little bit, but you know, relative to
the, you know, getting your training in
and making sure you're training, and I
always emphasize this to young athletes
and say is no supplement can make up for
a poor or a missed uh, workout. So, you
know, Yep. So, you're saying, and
correct me if I'm wrong, there really
you don't need any supplements. There's
nothing that's mandatory for you to see.
You can add in creatin
is good. I love my protein, but if
you're eating if you're getting your
protein through beef and chicken and
milk and whatever, you don't need the
whey protein supple. You want to get
your protein. If you can get that
through foods, great. If you're like me
and you, you like a morning shake or a
post-workout shake or a shake before you
go to sleep, that's perfectly fine. Go
for it. Cuz I have trouble getting in
all the protein through regular food per
day. Yeah. But it's not mandatory if you
can get it through food. Creatine can
help. Creatin creatine can help a couple
percentage points, but it's not going to
make this huge difference. And after
that, you know, maybe HMBB is
interesting. Yeah, fish oil is there's
lots of research on fish oil being
healthy for you, but you can get that
through eating fish. I don't really
recommend anything else because
again it takes the emphasis off of hard
training and sleep. If people just took
sleep more important and stress and
focused on their diet and focused on
their training, they'd see good results.
But people want, you know, they want a
panacea. They want this magic pill.
Yeah. And it all comes down to genetics
lay the foundation. Then you've got kind
of the training and the and the dieting
are equally as important. And then at
the top the very top of the pyramid is
supplementation.
And there's not, you know, the
supplements do do work, but it's not
it's this huge it's not the huge effects
that people think it is. It's the it's
the 1% the 2%. So make sure you're doing
everything else right. Yeah. Okay, Stu,
this was great. I appreciate your time.
Hope to have you on in the future. And
uh I should have reached out to you long
ago, but uh it's good to get you on now.
Thank you very much. I'm sure my readers
will like listening to this. I I hope
they do. It was my pleasure being with
you, Brett. Thanks very much. Okay.
Bye-bye. Bye-bye.